reversing insulin resistance is a Hot
Topic and for good reason because it
underlies so many different diseases in
a recent video doctor BOS an internal
medicine physician and ketogenic diet
proponent discussed three keys for
reversing this dreaded insulin
resistance we'll go through the video
add some context and studies to the
claims and then walk away with some key
points to implement sound good let's get
into it reversing insulin resistance
takes these three rules number one track
insulin not calories you may have heard
the rebuttal that your body does not
count calories and it's true but it does
not make you unaccountable instead of
obsessing on calories in versus calories
out we need you to focus on how much
insulin your body is producing your body
needs just one equation to be true to
put fat onto your body let me interject
here we'll get to the equation later the
two main points brought that by Dr BOS
are one that your body doesn't measure
calories and two you should focus on
insulin levels let's address them she's
absolutely right that your body has no
way of measuring or keeping track of
your calories because calories are
simply a unit of energy more
specifically heat however calories are a
direct proxy for the use or potential
use of very real molecules in all your
cells called ATP the main currency of
your cells so it's not like counting
calories as a waste of time it has
direct utility in fact while this has
little scientific value I've been
counting calories for 15 years to change
my weight up and down as needed now on
the other hand I like her point that it
doesn't make you unaccountable if you
decide to not count calories it's
absolutely true that no one has to count
calories but some form of measurement is
probably prudent if you want to your
goals like reversing insulin resistance
to her point you could measure insulin
levels but I think there's some context
that needs to be applied there which
we'll get into your body needs just one
equation to be true to put fat onto your
body it needs to have an elevated
insulin while consuming food
unfortunately insulin is very volatile
and sends you back and forth to the lab
several times before I know exactly what
it's doing we'll get to estimating your
insulin here in a minute but for now I
want to arm you with the knowledge of
what makes insulin rise causing you to
store fat the types of food matter carbs
cause the highest spike in insulin
whereas protein causes a lesser Spike
and fat causes the lowest spike in
insulin so that means we're eating fat
first and a lot of it don't look at the
calorie count remember when you're
consuming high fat that metabolism
starts to hike up not only does it have
the lowest production of insulin but
it's the best return on energy per bite
eating fat has the lowest amount of
insulin produced and when you consume
fat in a low insulin state it really
boosts the metabolism again you need the
insulin to store it as fat without that
insulin you get to use it as energy and
that's how metabolisms get boosted on a
high fat diet okay a few heavy hitting
points here some of which I agree with
and others I don't for fat to be stored
insulin must be high well there's a lot
of Truth to that but there's also some
reductionism going on it's true that
insulin does promote fat storage as well
as primarily reduce fat release from the
fat cells and stimulating fat production
in fat cells however the question is it
necessary as in must it be high for us
to gain body fat while there's no
denying insulin has a potent effect on
increasing body fat there are insulin
independ ways that cells can take up fat
molecules which is especially true when
fat consumption is significantly
increased for example in this study the
researchers measured the amount of fat
taken up by the cells when not exposed
to insulin and when exposed to insulin
as we can see by the data the amount of
fat taken up by the cells is on the
vertical axis and time passed is on the
horizontal axis the red squares are the
insulin stimulated cells clearly they
take up more fat but that's the Crux of
the issue the fact that I'm saying more
fat indicates other noninsulin
stimulated condition also took up fat
into the cells in addition fat molecules
are believed to passively move across
the cell membrane completely eliminating
the need for anything and if fat
concentrations are elevated in the blood
from greater fat consumption we now have
two insulin independent mechanisms for
encouraging fat uptake by the fat cells
that isn't to mention some others the
point being yes insulin is extremely
important but it's incorrect to assume
that it's the only Factor the next Point
brought up by DR Boss is that types a
food matter that raise insulin and she's
spot on in fact she was generous enough
to offer a scientific reference so we
can just lean on that and we can see
that data Dr boss's illustration is
perfect we can clearly see the lipids
that's fat only provide a mild rise in
insulin in addition a high-fat diet
increases metabolism according to Dr
boss that really depends on which
analysis that you look at this one or
this one one describes Zero Effect of a
high-fat diet compared against High
carbohydrate diets on metabolism the
other says a low carbohydrate diet
boosts metabolism compared to a high
carbohydrate diet so at the very least
there's some serious debate on that
point when looking at human trials the
final point for this section is tied up
in the first point you need insulin to
store fat but without insulin it gets
used as energy we've already discussed
the first part of that but the second
part has some truth to it when people
are fed a higher fat diet compared to a
lower fat High carbohydrate diet like in
this study their metabolism does switch
to burn more fat for
we can see that here the black bars
represent measure of metabolism called a
respiratory quotient if it goes down it
indicates more fat use for energy the
hf1 and hf7 conditions there are the
high fat groups and relative to LF or
lowfat high carbohydrate group there is
an increase in fat utilization for
energy again because the black bar is
going down one thing that's often left
out of this scenario is the fact that
while the body does switch to utilize
more fat when on a high-fat diet as we
just saw that doesn't necessarily make
it better at Fat Loss because you're
also consuming an outsized amount more
fat than normal like a counterweight on
the utilization of fat for energy I mean
this has been shown over and over again
like in these studies where a very low
carbohydrate ketogenic diet compared
against a high carbohydrate diet yielded
the same fat loss yet that shouldn't be
possible considering that the ketogenic
diet is the one with the strong insulin
advantage in the end the takeaway here
is that yes insulin is a major player in
fat gain but it isn't the only one
there's serious debate if a high-fat
diet actually increases metabolism
however a high-fat diet is still an
excellent way to lose body fat and
reverse signs of insulin resistance if
done correctly but there's more actually
before we go on I'm going to be
releasing an extended version of this
video that goes into more on reversing
insulin resistance including my
hierarchy of importance and some
alternatives on the ones outlined here
the extended version is included with
the physionic Insiders along with access
to all my work if you're so inclined
it's linked in the description box below
okay let's continue and then we'll
simplify everything for some simple
takeaways years of chronically elevated
insulin will take years to reverse so
stay focused on the high fat we'll shift
Focus later on in this story I've done
experiments where I've added a/4 cup of
MCT or medium chain triglycerides and
although I had added 500 calories to the
day I lost weight because of that
boosted metabolism in the presence of
the reduced insulin production so eat
the fat keep those carbs low under 20 G
per day Okay so so DR Boss takes an MCT
or a medium chain triglyceride
supplement that she sells and even takes
enough to make up 500 calories which is
a lot even so she lost weight I think
most health professionals would admit
that a single day fluctuation in weight
well that's pretty meaningless however
assuming that Dr boss did this for a
long time maybe it could be explained by
the research indicating a boost in
Metabolism from a high-fat diet although
that Research indicates more mild
increases in metabolism still while I'm
not skeptical of her experience it's
hers and I have no say I do find it hard
to believe that a person can add 500
calories of anything on top of their
usual diet on a regular basis and lose
body fat I've yet to see a study that
shows consuming 500 calories over
maintenance leads to fat loss but there
have been hundreds of fat loss studies
so we'll chalk this one up as
I don't know and move on to an
interesting concept brought up by DR
Boss number two don't eat after dark the
timing of those fat-based meals has a
profound impact on your insulin
production remember that even fat
produces a little bit of insulin and so
does the consumption of protein as well
as waking up in the morning that morning
rise of cortisol where your brain
intuitively knows that the sun is rising
sends a stimulus to your liver where the
production of glucose enters your body
and this spiking glucose results in a
spike in insulin if you're insulin
resistant we want to frontload those
meals earlier in the day put that
consumption of food in the daylight
hours the closest to Sunrise the better
eating after Sunset has a higher cost to
those with insulin resistance the longer
you get between your last bite of food
and the time you go to bed the better
your insulin will be the next day she's
referring to the dawn phenomenon and
she's absolutely right there tends to be
a higher cortisol blood sugar and
Insulin at the beginning of the day it's
also true that consuming your meals
earlier in the day will reduce insulin
levels later and especially the next
morning that's often discussed in the
context of intermittent fasting studies
too I'm not uh convinced that makes any
difference however because there have
been studies that maintain the same
nutrition but simply change the timing
of that nutrition and indicate no
differences in total daily insulin as in
the pancreas secretes the same total
insulin so if the overall goal is to
avoid insulin meal timing makes no
difference the caveat here is that the
study that I referenced was in healthy
individuals but I would suspect the same
is true for insulin resistant
individuals and there's even a little
bit of evidence out there for that
although there are some nuances to that
discussion that I can cover in the
future oh also uh none of the meals were
high fat so if you feel that makes a
difference on the overall point that may
change your view my educated guess is
that it makes no difference on total
insulin over a 24-hour period I'll post
an amendment if that turns out not to be
accurate one thing I can say in favor of
meal timing is that spikes of insulin
can be avoided by eating one's meals
more evenly spread throughout the day if
that matters to you anyway dawn
phenomenon is real but if total insulin
is something that you're trying to
reduce by frontloading your meals what
evidence exists does not corroborate
that perspective that I could find at
least now what about predicting your
insulin levels through this equation
that Dr BOS mentioned early on and
number three we have to measure it if we
want to change it if we want these rules
to stick we must measure the metrics so
we can study the improvements earlier I
said the measurement of insulin is messy
and indeed it is it's very volatile so
the best proxy for insulin is to measure
the two molecules that it controls the
most that being glucose and ketones
measuring glucose and ketones at the
same moment helps us use that metric in
combination to predict what your insulin
is we call this the Dr BOS ratio a
derivative of the gki or glucose Ketone
index the Dr BOS ratio uses the glucose
divided by the ketones and the lower the
Dr BOS ratio the lower the insulin Dr
BOS introduces the glucose Ketone index
or the Dr BOS index to measure or
predict insulin levels without having to
get your blood tested every day this is
a creative tool and I really like her
approach here if you want to know your
insulin levels without directly testing
them the higher your ketones and lower
your glucose the bet is great that your
insulin levels are low like I said this
is a creat clever and really a great tip
especially for people who don't have the
luxury of an atome insulin test okay
that was a lot of back and forth across
all of what was said what's the takeaway
here the takeaway is that while I
disagree with some of the finer points
made by DR Boss because I don't think
that they stack up to the available
evidence none of that
disagreement is with the overall idea
that a high fat diet can be an excellent
method for for reversing many signs of
insulin resistance it can provide uh fat
loss which improves insulin resistance
but it can also dramatically lower blood
sugar and insulin levels independently
of fat loss I would likely encourage a
person to focus on unsaturated forms of
fat and I would also add that other
nutrition Styles have been shown to also
be effective at reversing insulin
resistance including High carbohydrate
nutrition but if you're focused on a
high fat uh for any of several
advantages that it offers then it can be
an excellent choice I also don't agree
that meal timing makes much of a
difference in total insulin but if you
care about insulin spikes it can make a
difference there finally the glucose
Ketone ratio is great it's a quick
method for estimating insulin levels
without needing dedicated insulin test
in fact I have other content that
describes ways of reversing diabetes and
general insulin resistance right here
I'll see you over there a
[Music]